Alexander James Wallar

Email: wallar@mit.edu , Website: http://wallar.me, Phone: +1 240-470-8491 32 Vassar St. Room 376, Cambridge, MA 02139

Summary

Alex Wallar is a PhD student in the Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory at MIT. His research focusses optimizing vehicle distributions and fleet sizes for ride-sharing systems in order to maximize system efficiency. He is a recipient of the Lemelson Presidential Fellowship, the MIT Diversity Fellowship, and the Shell-MIT Energy Fellowship. He received his masters degree in Electrical Engineering and Computer Science from MIT in 2017 with a focus on applications of constrained optimization for mobility-on-demand systems. He received his Bachelors degree in Computer Science from the University of St. Andrews in 2015 with first class honours.

Education

Ph.D. Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Sept 2017 – present Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA

Advisor: Prof. Daniela Rus

S.M. Electrical Engineering and Computer Science Sept 2015 – June 2017

Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA

Advisor: Prof. Daniela Rus

GPA: 5.0/5.0

B.Sc. (Honours) Computer Science Sept 2012 – June 2015

University of St Andrews, St Andrews, Scotland

First Class Honours Degree Classification

Direct Entry Into Second Year

Experience

Lead Software Engineer

July 2017 - present

Enki Cards, Cambridge
Lead the development of the front-end and back-end for Enki Cards, a startup in Cambridge creating 3D foldable greeting cards

Research Scientist Intern

May 2016 – Aug 2016

Research and Development Group

Amazon Robotics, Boston

• Analyzed and developed algorithms for drive prioritization in order to reduce floor congestion

Research Scientist (Contractor)

Jan 2015 – Aug 2015

May 2014 - Aug 2014

Distributed Autonomous Systems Group

Naval Research Laboratory, Washington DC

• Developed algorithms for multi-agent persistent surveillance of risk sensitive areas

Research Intern

Distributed Autonomous Systems Group

Naval Research Laboratory, Washington DC

• Developed algorithms for persistent surveillance and collision avoidance

NSF Research Intern

May 2013 – Aug 2013

Experiment Research in Wireless Networking Group

University of Notre Dame, South Bend

• Created a JavaScript library for in-browser eye tracking and gaze prediction

Publications

- 1. A. Wallar, J. Alonso-Mora, and D. Rus (2018): Optimizing Vehicle Distributions and Fleet Sizes for Mobility-on-Demand. *conference*, *submitted*
- B. Araki, I. Gilitschenski, T. Ogata, A. Wallar, W. Schwarting, Z.Choudhury, S. Karaman, and D. Rus (2018): Range-based Cooperative Localization with Nonlinear Observability Analysis. conference, submitted
- 3. A. Wallar, M. van der Zee, J. Alonso-Mora, and D. Rus (2018): Vehicle Rebalancing for Mobility-on-Demand Systems with Ride-Sharing. *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, accepted
- 4. **A. Wallar**, B. Araki, R. Chang, J. Alonso-Mora, and D. Rus (2017): Foresight: Remote Sensing For Autonomous Vehicles Using a Small Unmanned Aerial Vehicle. *Field and Service Robotics*, pp. 591 604
- 5. J. Alonso-Mora, A. Wallar, and D. Rus (2017): Predictive Routing for Autonomous Mobility-On-Demand Systems with Ride-Sharing. *IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS)*, pp. 3583 3590
- J. Alonso-Mora, S. Samaranayake, A. Wallar, E. Frazzoli, and D. Rus (2017): On-demand High-capacity Ride-sharing via Dynamic Trip-vehicle Assignment. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, vol. 114, no. 3, pp. 462 – 467
- A. Wallar, E. Plaku, and D. Sofge (2015): Reactive Motion Planning for Unmanned Aerial Surveillance of Risk-Sensitive Areas. *IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering*, vol. 12, issue 3, pp. 969 980
- 8. D. Sofge, N. Sydney, A. Wallar, and K. Sullivan (2015): Mobile Autonomous Navy Teams for Information Surveillance and Search (MANTISS). *Naval Research Laboratory Review*, pp. 155–157
- 9. **A.** Wallar and E. Plaku (2014): Path Planning for Swarms in Dynamic Environments by Combining Probabilistic Roadmaps and Potential Fields. *IEEE Symposium on Swarm Intelligence*
- 10. **A. Wallar**, E. Plaku, and D. Sofge (2014): A Planner for Autonomous Risk-Sensitive Coverage (PARCov) by a Team of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles. *IEEE Symposium on Swarm Intelligence*
- 11. **A. Wallar** and E. Plaku (2014): Path Planning for Swarms by Combining Probabilistic Roadmaps and Potential Fields. *Springer LNAI Towards Autonomous Robotic Systems*, vol. 8069, pp. 417 428

Patents

- J. Alonso-Mora, S. Samaranayake, A. Wallar, and D. Rus (2018): System for On-Demand High-Capacity Ride-Sharing Via Dynamic Trip-Vehicle Assignment and Related Techniques. U.S. Patent Application 15/877,935
- 2. J. Alonso-Mora, D. Rus, and **A. Wallar** (2018): On-Demand High-Capacity Ride-Sharing Via Dynamic Trip-Vehicle Assignment with Future Requests. *U.S. Patent Application* 15/941,449

Theses

- 1. **A. Wallar** (2017): On-demand High-capacity Ride-sharing via Dynamic Trip-Vehicle Assignment with Rebalancing. S.M. Thesis. Massachusetts Institute of Technology
- 2. A. Wallar (2015): Generating Safe Trajectories in Stochastic Dynamic Environments by Leveraging Information About Obstacle Motion. Undergraduate Thesis. University of St Andrews

Awards

- Shell-MIT Energy Fellowship, MIT, 2018 19
- Finalist, MIT \$100K Pitch Competition, 2018
- School of Engineering Lemelson Presidential Fellowship, MIT, 2015 16
- Office of the Dean of Graduate Education Diversity Fellowship, MIT, 2015 16
- Travel Award, IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence, 2014
- Dean's List, University of St Andrews, 2012 15
- Best Poster Prize, University of Notre Dame NSF REU Conference, 2013
- Winner, J.P. Morgan Code for Good Hackathon, 2013
- Second place, KCL Tech Society HackKing's Hackathon, 2014

Developer Skills

Languages: Python, C++, Java, JavaScript, Matlab, Go, C#

Tools: ROS, OpenCV, ZeroMQ, Flask, NumPy, SciPy, Scikit-Learn, Keras, InfluxDB, RethinkDB, three.js

Courses

Massachusetts Institute of Technology: Advances in Computer Vision, Advanced Algorithms, Computer Networks, User Interface Design and Implementation, Airport Systems

University of St Andrews: Foundations of Computation (Accelerated), Advanced Programming Projects, Advanced Computer Science, Discrete Mathematics, Software Engineering, Data Encoding, Operating Systems, Computational Complexity, Artificial Intelligence, Component Technology, Major Software Team Project, Video Games, Artificial Intelligence Practice, Logic and Software Verification, Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining, Distributed Systems, Constraint Programming, Major Software Project